<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands new chains discovered; or The serious apprehensions of a part of the people, in behalf of the Commonwealth; (being presenters, promoters, and approvers of the large petition of September 11. 1648.) Presented to the supreme authority of England, the representers of the people in Parliament assembled. / By Lieut. Col. John Lilburn, and divers other citizens of London, and borough of Southwark; February 26. 1648. whereunto his speech delivered at the bar is annexed.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E545_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204425</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863919</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88182)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E545[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands new chains discovered; or The serious apprehensions of a part of the people, in behalf of the Commonwealth; (being presenters, promoters, and approvers of the large petition of September 11. 1648.) Presented to the supreme authority of England, the representers of the people in Parliament assembled. / By Lieut. Col. John Lilburn, and divers other citizens of London, and borough of Southwark; February 26. 1648. whereunto his speech delivered at the bar is annexed.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 1st 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  1642-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS <hi>NEW CHAINS</hi> DISCOVERED: Or The ſerious apprehenſions of a part of the People, in behalf of the Commonwealth; (being Preſenters, Promoters, and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Large Petition of <hi>September 11. 1648.</hi>)</head>
            <head>Preſented to the Supreme Authority of England, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters of the people in Parliament aſſembled.</head>
            <byline>By Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and divers other Citizens of London, and Borough of Southwark; February <hi>26. 1648</hi> whereunto his ſpeech delivered at the Bar is annexed.</byline>
            <p>SInce you have done the Nation ſo much right, and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves ſo much honour as to declare that the People (under God) are the original of all juſt Powers; and given us thereby fair grounds to hope, that you really intend their Freedom and Proſperity; yet the way thereunto being frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtaken, and through haſt or error of judgement, thoſe who me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the beſt, are many times miſ-led ſo far to the prejudice of thoſe that truſt them, as to leave them in a condition neereſt to bondage, when they have thought they had brought them into a way of Freedom. And ſince woful experience hath manifeſted this to be a Truth, there ſeemeth no ſmall reaſon that you ſhould ſeriouſly lay to heart what at preſent we have to offer, for diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and prevention of ſo great a danger.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we have bin the firſt movers in and concerning a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> as the moſt proper and juſt means for the ſetling the long and tedious diſtractions of this Nation, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by nothing more, than the uncertainty of our government; and ſince there hath bin an Agreement prepared and preſented by ſome Officers of the Army to this honourable Houſe, as what they thought requiſite to be agreed unto by the People (you approving thereof) we ſhall in the firſt place deliver our apprehenſions thereupon.</p>
            <p>That an Agreement between thoſe that truſt, and thoſe who are truſted, hath appeared a thing acceptable to this honorable Houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:116135:2"/>
his Excellency, and the Officers of the Army, is as much to our rejoycing, as we conceive it juſt in it ſelf, and profitable for the Common-wealth, and cannot doubt but that you will protect thoſe of the people, who have no waies forfeited their Birth-right, in their proper liberty of taking this, or any other, as God and their own Conſiderationss ſhall direct them.</p>
            <p>Which we the rather mention, for that many particulars in the Agreement before you, are upon ſerious examination thereof, diſ-ſatisfactory to moſt of thoſe who are very earneſtly deſirous of an Agreement, and many very material things ſeem to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theren, which may be ſupplyed in another; As</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are now much troubled there ſhould be any Intervalls between he ending of this Repreſentative, and the begining of the next as being deſirous that this preſent Parliament that hath ately done ſo great things in ſo ſhort a time, tending to their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, ſhould ſit; until with certainty and ſafety they can ſee them deivered into the hands of another Repreſentative, rather than to eave them (though never ſo ſmall a time) under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of a Councel of State; a Conſtitution of a new and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced Nature, and which they fear, as the caſe now ſtands, may deſign to perpetuate their power, and to keep off Parliaments for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They now conceive no leſs danger, in that it is provided that Parliaments for the future are to continue but 6. moneths, and a Councel of State 18. In which time, if they ſhould prove cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, having command of all Forces by Sea and Land, they will have great opportunities to make themſelves abſolute and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable: And becauſe this is a danger, than which there cannot well be a greater; they generally incline to Annual Parliaments, bounded and limited as reaſon ſhall deviſe, not diſſolvable, but to be continued or adjourned as ſhall ſeem good in their diſcretion, during that yeer, but no longer; and then to diſſolve of courſe, and give way to thoſe who ſhall be choſen immediatly to ſucceed them, and in the Intervals of their adjournments, to entruſt an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Committee of their own members, as in other caſes limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bounded with expreſs inſtructions, and accountable to the next Seſſion, which will avoid all thoſe dangers feared from a Councel of State, as at preſent this is conſtituted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are not ſatisfied with the clauſe, whereas it is ſaid, <hi>that
<pb facs="tcp:116135:2"/>
the power of the Repreſentative ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the erecting and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing of Courts of Iuſtice;</hi> ſince the alteration of the uſual way of Tryals by twelve ſworn men of the Neighborhood, may be included therein: a conſtitution ſo equal and juſt in it ſelf, as that they conceive it ought to remain unalterable. Neither is it cleer what is meant by theſe words, <hi>(viz.) That the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives have the higheſt final judgement.</hi> They conceiving that their Authority in theſe caſes, is onely to make Laws, Rules, and Directions for other Courts and Perſon; aſſigned by Law for the execution thereof, unto which every member of the Common-wealth, as well thoſe of the Repreſentative, as others, ſhould be alike ſubject; it being likewiſe unreaſonable in it ſelf, and an occaſion of much partiality, injuſtice, and vexation to the people, that the Law-makers, ſhould be Law-executors.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Although it doth provide that in the Laws hereafter to be made, no perſon by vertue of any Tenure, Grant, Charter, Parent, Degree, or Birth, ſhall be priviledged from ſubjection thereunto, or from being bound thereby, as well as others; Yet doth it not null and make void thoſe preſent Protections by Law, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; nor leave all perſons, as well Lords as others, alike liable in perſon and eſtate, as in reaſon and conſcience they ought to be.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are very much unſatisfied with what is expreſt as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from the Repreſentative, in matters of Religion, as being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſcure, and full of perplexity, that ought to be moſt plain and clear; there having occurred no greater trouble to the Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any thing than by the intermedling of Parliaments in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They ſeem to conceive it abſolutely neceſſary, that there be in their Agreement, a reſerve from ever having any Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and a bar againſt reſtoring the Houſe of Lords, both which are wanting in the Agreement which is before you.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They ſeem to be reſolved to take away all known and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome grievances, as Tythes, that great oppreſſion of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries induſtry and hindrance of Tillage: Exciſe, and Cuſtoms, Thoſe ſecret thieves, and Robbers, Drainers of the poor and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſort of People, and the greateſt Obſtructers of Trade, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting all the prejudices of Ship-mony, Pattents, and Projects, before this Parliament: alſo to take away all Monopolizing Companies of Marchants, the hinderers and decayers of Clothing
<pb facs="tcp:116135:3"/>
and Cloth-working, Dying, and the like uſeful profeſſions; by which thouſands of poor people might be ſet at work, that are now ready to ſtarve, were Marchandizing reſtored to its due and proper freedom: they conceive likewiſe that the three grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before mentioned, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Monopolizing Companies, Exciſe, and Cuſtomes, do exceedingly prejudice Shiping, and Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Conſequently diſcourage Sea-men, and Marriners, and which have had no ſmal influence upon the late unhappy revolts which have ſo much endangered the Nation, and ſo much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged your enemies. They alſo incline to direct a more equal and leſſe burdenſome way for levying monies for the future, thoſe other fore-mentioned being ſo chargable in the receipt, as that the very ſtipends and allowance to the Officers attending thereupon would defray a very great part of the charge of the Army; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now they engender and ſupport a corrupt intereſt. They alſo have in mind to take away all impriſonment of diſabled men, for debt; and to provide ſome effectual courſe to enforce all that are able to a ſpeedy payment, and not ſuffer them to be ſheltered in Priſons, where they live in plenty, whilſt their Creditors are undone. They have alſo in mind to provide work, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maintainance for all ſorts of poor, aged, and impotent people, and to eſtabliſh ſome more ſpeedy, leſſe troubleſome and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able way for deciding of Controverſies in Law, whole families having been ruined by ſeeking right in the wayes yet in being: All which (though of greateſt and moſt immediate concernment to the People, are yet omitted in their Agreement before you.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like are their intentions in what they purpoſe for an Agreement of the People, as being reſolved (ſo far as they are able) to lay an impoſſibility upon all whom they ſhall hereafter truſt, of ever wronging the Common wealth in any conſiderable meaſure, without certainty of ruining themſelves, and as concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to be an improper tedious, and unprofitable thing for the People, to be ever runing after their Repreſentatives with Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for redreſſe of ſuch Grievances as may at once be removed by themſelves, or to depend for theſe things ſo eſſential to their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and freedom, upon the uncertain judgements of ſeveral Repreſentatives, the one being apt to renew what the other hath taken away.</p>
            <p>And as to the uſe of their Rights and Liberties herein as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb facs="tcp:116135:3"/>
and is due to the people, from whom all juſt powers are deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; they hoped for and expect what protection is in you and the Army to afford: and we likewiſe in their and our own behalfe do earneſtly deſire, that you will publikely declare your reſolution to protect thoſe who have not forfeited their liberties in the uſe thereof, leſt they ſhould conceive that the Agreement before you being publiſhed abroad, and the Commiſſioners therein nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being at work in perſuance thereof, is intended to be impoſed upon them, which as it is abſolutely contrary to the nature of a free Agreement, ſo we are perſwaded it cannot enter into your thoughts to uſe any impulſion therein.</p>
            <p>But although we have preſented our apprehenſions and deſires concerning this great work of an Agreement, and are apt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelves that nothing ſhall be able to fruſtrate our hopes which we have built thereupon; yet have we ſeen and heard ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things of late, which occaſions not only apprehenſions of other matters intended to be brought upon us of danger to ſuch an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, but of bondage and ruine to all ſuch as ſhall purſue it.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that we are even agaſt and aſtoniſhed to ſee that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the productions of the higheſt notions of freedom that ever this Nation, or any people in the world, have brought to light, notwithſtanding the vaſt expece of blood and treaſure that hath been made to purchaſe thoſe freedoms, notwithſtanding the many eminent and even miraculous Victories God hath been pleaſed to honour our juſt Cauſe withall, notwithſtanding the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gripes and pangs, this Houſe hath ſuffered more than once at the hands of your own ſervants, and that at leaſt ſeemingly for the obtaining theſe our Native Liberties.</p>
            <p>When we conſider what rackings and tortures the People in general have ſuffered through decay of Trade, and deerneſſe of food, and very many families in particular, through Free-quarter, Violence, and other miſeries, incident to warre, having nothing to ſupport them therein, but hopes of Freedom, and a well-ſetled Common-wealth in the end.</p>
            <p>That yet after all theſe things have bin done and ſuffered, and whilſt the way of an Agreement of the People is owned, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, even by your ſelves, and that all men are in expectation of being put into poſſeſſion of ſo deer a purchaſe; Behold! in the cloſe of all, we hear and ſee what gives us freſh and pregnant cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:116135:4"/>
to believe that the contrary is really intended, and that all thoſe ſpecious pretenſes, and high Notions of Liberty, with thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary courſes that have of late bin taken (as if of neceſſity for liberty, and which indeed can never be juſtified, but deſerve the greateſt puniſhments, unleſs they end in juſt liberty, and an equal Government) appear to us to have bin done and directed by ſome ſecret powerful influences, the more ſecurely and unſuſpectedly to attain to an abſolute domination over the Common-wealth: it being impoſſible for them, but by aſſuming our generally appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Principles, and hiding under the fair ſhew thereof their other deſigns, to have drawn in ſo many good and godly men (really aiming at what the other had but in ſhew and pretenſe) and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them unwittingly inſtrumental to their own and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Bondage.</p>
            <p>For where is that good, or where is that liberty ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, ſo deerly purchaſed? If we look upon what this Houſe hath done ſince it hath voted it ſelf the Supreme Authority, and disburthened themſelves of the power of the Lords. Firſt, we find a high Court of Juſtice erected, for Tryal of Criminal cauſes; whereby that great and ſtrong hold of our preſervation, the way of tryal by 12. ſworn men of the Neighborhood is infringed, all liberty of exception againſt the tryers, is over-ruled by a Court conſiſting of perſons pickt and choſen in an un-uſual way; the practiſe whereof we cannot allow of, though againſt open and notorious enemies; as well becauſe we know it to be an uſual po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to introduce by ſuch means all uſurpations, firſt againſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, in hope of eaſier admiſſion; as alſo, for that the ſame being ſo admited, may at pleaſure be exerciſed againſt any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever. This is the firſt part of our new liberty. The next is the cenſuring of a Member of this Houſe, for declaring his judgement in a point of Religion, which is directly oppoſite to the Reſerve in the Agreement concerning Religion. Beſides the Act for preſſing of Sea-men, directly contrary to the Agreement of the Officers. Then the ſtoping of our mouths from Printing, is carefully provided for, and the moſt ſevere and unreaſonable Ordinances of Parliament that were made in the time of <hi>Hollis</hi> and <hi>Stapletons</hi> reign, to gag us from ſpeaking truth, and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tyrannies of bad men, are refered to the care of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and by him to his Marſhal, to be put in execution; in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:116135:4"/>
fining, impriſoning, and other waies corporally puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that any waies be guilty of unlicenſed Printing; They dealing with us as the Biſhops of old did with the honeſt Puritan, who were exact in geting Laws made againſt the Papiſt, but really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them againſt the Puritan, and made them feel the ſmart of them: Which alſo hath bin, and is dayly exerciſed moſt violently, whereby our Liberties have bin more deeply wounded, than ſince the begining of this Parliament; and that to the diſlike of the Souldiery, as by their late Petition in that behalf plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Then whereas it was expected that the Chancery, and Courts of Juſtice in Weſtminſter, and the Judges and Officers thereof ſhould have bin ſurveyed, and for the preſent regulated, till a better and more equal way of deciding controverſies could have bin conſtituted, that the trouble and charge of the people in their ſuits ſhould have bin abated: Inſteed hereof, the old and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced fees are continued, and new thouſand pounds Annual ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends alotted; when in the corrupteſt times the ordinary fees were thought a great and a ſore burden; in the mean time, and in lieu thereof, there is not one perplexity or abſurdity in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings taken away. Thoſe Petitioners that have moved in behalf of the people, how have they bin entertained? Somtimes with the complement of empty thanks, their deſires in the mean time not at all conſidered; at other times meeting with Reproches and Threats for their conſtancy and publike affections, and with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motions, that their Petitions be burnt by the common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whilſt others are not taken in at all; to ſo ſmall an account are the people brought, even while they are flattered with notions of being the Original of all juſt power. And laſtly, for compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this new kind of liberty, a Councel of State is haſtily erected for Guardians thereof, who to that end are poſſeſſed with power to order and diſpoſe all the forces appertaining to England by Sea or Land, to diſpoſe of the publike Treaſure, to command any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever before them, to give oath for the diſcovering of Truth, to impriſon any that ſhall diſ-obey their commands, and ſuch as they ſhall judge contumatious. What now is become of that liberty that no mans perſon ſhall be attached or impriſoned, or otherwiſe diſ-eaſed of his Free-hold, or free Cuſtoms, but by lawful judgement of his equals? We entreat you give us leave to lay theſe things open to your <hi>vie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and judge impartially of our
<pb facs="tcp:116135:5"/>
preſent condition, and of your own alſo, that by ſtrong and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull influences of ſome perſons, are put upon theſe and the like proceedings, which both you and we ere long (if we look not to it) ſhall be inforced to ſubject our ſelves unto; then we have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe to complain, when we conſider the perſons: as firſt, the chief of the Army directly contrary to what themſelves thought meet in their Agreement for the People. 2. Judges of the Law, and Treaſurers for monies. Then 5. that were Members of the Lords Houſe, and moſt of them ſuch as have refuſed to approve of your Votes and proceedings, concerning the King and Lords. 2. of them Judges in the Star-chamber, and approvers of the bloudy and tyrannical ſentences iſſuing from thence.</p>
            <p>Some of your own Houſe, forward men in the Treaty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliners of your laſt proceedings; all which do cleerly manifeſt to our underſtandings that the ſecret contrivers of thoſe things doe think themſelves now ſo ſurely guarded by the ſtrength of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by their dayly Acts and Stratagems, to their ends inclined, and the captivation of this Houſe, that they may now take off the Vail and Cloak of their deſignes as dreadleſſe of what ever can be done againſt them. By this Councel of State, all power is got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own hands, a project which hath been long and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly laboured for; and which being once firmly and to their liking eſtabliſhed their next motions may be upon pretenſe of eaſe to the People, for the diſſolution of this Parliament, half of whoſe time is already ſwallowed up by the ſaid Councel: now becauſe no obſtacle lies in their way, to the full eſtabliſhment of theſe their ends: but the uncorrupted part of the Souldiery, that have their eyes fixed upon their ingagements and promiſes of good to the People, and reſolve by no threats or allurements to decline the ſame; together with that part of the people in Citie and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that remain conſtant in their motions for Common good, and ſtill perſiſt to run their utmoſt hazards for procurement of the ſame, by whom all evil mens deſignes both have, and are ſtill like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to find a check and diſcovery. Hereupon the grand contrivers fore-mentioned, whom we can particular by name, do begin to raiſe their ſpleen, and manifeſt a more violent enmitie againſt Souldiers and People, diſpoſed as afore-ſaid, than ever hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as appeareth by what lately paſt, at a meeting of Officers, on <hi>Feb.</hi> 22. laſt, at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> where after expreſſions of much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:116135:5"/>
againſt the moſt Conſciencious paſt of the Souldiery, and others, it was inſiſted upon, (as we are from very credible hands certainly informed) that a motion ſhould be made to this Houſe for the procurement of a Law enabling them to put to death all ſuch as they ſhould judge by Petitions or otherwiſe to diſturbe the preſent proceedings; and upon urging that the Civil Magiſtrate ſhould do it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was anſwered, that they could hang twenty ere the Magiſtrate one. It was likewiſe urged that Orders might be given to ſeize upon the Petitioners, Souldiers, or others, at their meetings, with much exclamation againſt ſome of greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie to your juſt Authority, whereof they have given continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and undenyable aſſurances. A Proclamation was likewiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, forbidding the Souldiers to Petition you, or any but their Officers, prohibiting their correſpondencies: And private Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be given out for ſeizing upon Citizens and Souldiers at their meetings. And thus after theſe fair bloſſoms of hopefull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, breaks forth this bitter fruit, of the vileſt and baſeſt bondage that ever Engliſh men groan'd under: whereby this notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is gained <hi>(viz.)</hi> an evident and (we hope) a timely diſcovery of the inſtruments, from whence all the evils, contrivances, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes (which for above theſe eighteen moneths have been ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpected) took their riſe and original, even ever ſince the firſt breach of their Promiſes and engagements made at <hi>New Market, Triploe Heath,</hi> with the Agitators and People. It being for theſe ends that they have ſo violently oppoſed all ſuch as manifeſted any zeal for Common Right, or any regard to the Faith of the Army, ſentencing ſome to death, others to reproachfull puniſhments, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and diſ-placing Officers according as they ſhewed themſelves ſerviceable or oppoſite to their deſignes, liſting as many as they thought good, even of ſuch as have ſerved in Arms againſt you: And then again upon pretence of eaſing the charge of the People, disbanding Supernumeraries, by advantage thereof picking out, ſuch as were moſt cordial and active for Common good; thereby moulding the Army (as far as they could) to their own bent and ends premiſed; exerciſing Martial-Law with much cruelty, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to debaſe their ſpirits, and make them ſubſervient to their wils and pleaſures; extending likewiſe their power (in many caſes) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſons not Members of the Army.</p>
            <p>And when in caſe of oppoſition and difficult ſervices, they have
<pb facs="tcp:116135:6"/>
by their creatures deſired a Reconciliation with ſuch as at other times they reproached, vilified, and otherwiſe abaſed; and through fair promiſes of good, and diſſembled repentance gained their aſſociation and aſſiſtance, to the great advantage of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: yet their neceſſities being over, and the Common enemy ſubdued, they have ſleighted their former promiſes, and renewed their hate and bitterneſſe againſt ſuch their aſſiſtances, reproaching them with ſuch appellations as they knew did moſt diſtaſte the People, ſuch as Levellers, Jeſuites, Anarchiſts, Royaliſts names, both contradictory in themſelves, and altogether groundleſſe in relation to the men ſo reputed; meerly relying for releefe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon the eaſineſſe and credulity of the People.</p>
            <p>And though the better to inſinuate themſelves, and get repute with the People, as alſo to conquer their neceſſities, they have bin fane to make uſe of thoſe very principles and productions, the men they have ſo much traduced, have brought to light: yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers themſelves they have and doe ſtill more eagerly maligne than ever, as ſuch whom they know to bee acquainted to their deceipts, and deviations and beſt able to diſcover the ſame.</p>
            <p>So that now at length, gueſſing all to be ſure, and their own (the King being removed, the Houſe of Lords nulled, their long plotted Councel of State erected, and this Houſe awed to their ends,) the edge of their mallice is turning againſt ſuch as have yet ſo much courage left them as to appear for the well eſtabliſhment of Englands Liberties: and becauſe God hath preſerved a great part of the Army untainted with the guilt of the deſignes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, who cannot without much danger to the deſigners themſelves be ſuppreſſed, they have reſolved to put this Houſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on raiſing more new forces, (notwithſtanding the preſent neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the People, in maintaining thoſe that are already) in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof (though the pretence be danger, and oppoſition, yet the concealed end is like to be the over-ballancing thoſe in the Army, who are reſolved to ſtand for true Freedome, as the end of all their labours, the which (if they ſhould be permitted to do) they would not then doubt of making themſelves abſolute ſeizures, Lords and Maſters, both of Parliament and People; which when they have done we expect the utmoſt of miſery, nor ſhall it grieve us to expire with the liberties of out native Country: for what good man can with any comfort to himſelf ſurvive then? But
<pb facs="tcp:116135:6"/>
God hath hitherto preſerved us, and the Juſtice of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> integrity of our intentions are dayly more and more manifeſt to the impartial and unprejudiced part of men; inſomuch that it is no ſmal comfort to us, that notwithſtanding we are upon all theſe diſadvantages that may be, having neither power nor prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, the Common Idols of the world; our Cauſe and princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, do through their own natural truth and luſtre get ground in mens underſtandings, ſo that where there was one, twelve mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths ſince, that owned our principles, we beleeve there are now hundreds, ſo that though we fail, our Truths proſper.</p>
            <p>And poſterity we doubt not ſhall reap the benefit of our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, what ever ſhall become of us. However though we have neither ſtrength nor ſafety before us, we have diſcharged our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and emptied our breaſts unto you, knowing well that if you will muke uſe of your power, and take unto you that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage which becomes men of your Truſt and condition, you may yet through the goodneſſe of God prevent the danger and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief intended, and be inſtrumental in reſtoring this long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled and betrayed Nation into a good and happy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For which end we moſt earneſtly deſire and propoſe, as the main prop and ſupport of the work, that you will not diſſolve this Houſe, nor ſuffer your ſelves to be diſſolved, until as aforeſaid, you ſee a new Repreſentative the next day ready to take your room; which you may confidently and ſafely inſiſt upon, there being no conſiderable number in the Army or elſe-where, that will be ſo unworthy as to dare to diſturb you therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you will put in practiſe the ſelf-denying Ordinance, the moſt juſt and uſeful that ever was made, and continually cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out for by the people; whereby a great infamy that lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your cauſe will be removed, and men of powerful influences, and dangerous deſignes, deprived of thoſe means and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which now they have, to prejudice the publike.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That you will conſider how dangerous it is for one and the ſame perſons to be continued long in the higheſt commands of a Military power, eſpecially acting ſo long diſtinct, and of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as thoſe now in being have done, and in ſuch extraordinary waies whereunto they have accuſtomed themſelves, which was
<pb facs="tcp:116135:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:116135:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:116135:8"/>
the original of moſt Regalities and Tyrannies in the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That you appoint a Committee of ſuch of your own mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as have bin longeſt eſtabliſht upon thoſe rules of Freedom upon which you now proceed; to hear, examine, and conclude all controverſies between Officers and Officers, and between Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers; to conſider and mitigate the Law-Martial; and to provide that it be not exerciſed at all, upon perſons not of the Army: Alſo to releaſe and repair ſuch as have thereby unduly ſuffered, as they ſhall ſee cauſe: To conſider the condition of the private Souldiers, both Horſe and Foot in theſe deer times, and to allow them ſuch increaſe of pay, as wherewithal they may live comfortably, and honeſtly diſcharge their Quarters: That all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding be refered to the ſaid Committee, and that ſuch of the Army as have ſerved the King, may be firſt disbanded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That you will open the Preſs, whereby all trecherous and tyranical deſignes may be the eaſier diſcovered, and ſo prevented, which is a liberty of greateſt concernment to the Commonwealth, and which ſuch only as intend a tyrannie are engaged to prohibit: The mouths of Adverſaries being beſt ſtopped, by the ſenſible good which the people receive from the actions of ſuch as are in Authority.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That you wil (whilſt you have opportunity) abate the charge of the Law, and reduce the ſtipends of Judges, and all other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Officers in the Common-wealth, to a leſs, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent allowance, converting the over-plus to the publike Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, whereby the taxes of the people may be much eaſed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But above all, that you will diſſolve this preſent Councel of State, which upon the grounds fore-mentioned ſo much threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Tyrannie; and mannage your affairs by Committees of ſhort continuance, and ſuch as may be frequently and exactly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for the diſcharge of their Truſts.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That you will publiſh a ſtrict prohibition, and ſevere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty againſt all ſuch, whether Committees, Magiſtrates, or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of what kind ſoever, as ſhall exceed the limits of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Rules, or Directions, and incourage all men in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations and complaints againſt them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That you will ſpeedily ſatisfie the expectations of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in point of Arrears, and of the people in point of Accounts, in ſuch a manner, as that it may not as formerly, prove a ſnare to
<pb facs="tcp:116135:8"/>
ſuch as have bin moſt faithful, and a protection to the moſt corrupt, in the diſcharge of their truſt and duties.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That the ſo many times complained of Ordinance for Tyths upon treble damages, may be forthwith taken away; all which, together with due regard ſhewed to Petitioners, without reſpect to their number and ſtrength, would ſo faſten you in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the people, and of the honeſt Officers and Souldiers, as that you ſhould not need to fear any oppoſite power whatſoever: and for the time to come, of your ſelves enjoy the exerciſe of your Supreme Authority, whereof you have yet but the name onely; and be inabled to vindicate your juſt undertakings; wherein we ſhould not onely rejoyce to have occaſion to manifeſt how ready we ſhould be to hazard our lives in your behalf, but ſhould alſo bend all our ſtudies and endeavours to render you Honorable to all future generations.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:116135:9"/>
            <head>
               <date>Febr. 26. 1648.</date> Being ushered in by the Sergeant at Arms, and called to the Bar, with all due reſpects gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the Houſe, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> with divers others, coming to the Bar next the Mace, with the Addreſs in his hand, ſpake theſe words, or to this effect, as followeth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am very glad that without any inconvenience unto my ſelf, and thoſe that are with me, I may freely and cheerfully addreſs my ſelf to this honorable Houſe, as the Supreme Authority of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (time was when I could not) and it much refreſheth my ſpirit, to live to ſee this day, that yon have made ſuch a ſtep to the Peoples Liberties, as to own and declare your ſelves to be (as indeed you are) the Supreme Authority of this Nation.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I am deſired by a company of honeſt men, living in and about London, who in truth do rightly appropriate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the title of the Contrivers, Promoters, Preſenters, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provers of the late Large London Petition of the <hi>11.</hi> of <hi>Sept.</hi> laſt, (which was the firſt Petition I know of in England, that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to this honorable Houſe againſt the late deſtructive Perſonal Treaty with the late King) to preſent you with their ſerious appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions; And give me leave (I beſeech you) for my ſelf and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, to ſay thus much; That for the moſt part of us, we are thoſe that in the worſt of times durſt own our Liberties and Freedoms, in the face of the greateſt of our adverſaries; and from the begiting of theſe Wars, never ſhrunk from the owning of our Freedoms, in the moſt tempeſtuous times, nor changed our Principles: Nay <hi>Sir,</hi> let me with truth tell you, that to the moſt of us, our Wives, our Children, our Eſtates, our Relations, nay our Lives, and all that upon earth we can call Ours, have not bin ſo highly valued by us, as our Liberties and Freedoms; which our constant Actions (to the apparent hazard of our Bloud and Lives) have bin a cleer and full demonſtration of, for theſe many yeers together.</p>
            <p>And M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> give me leave to tell you, that I am confident our Liberties and Freedoms (the true and juſt end of all the late
<pb facs="tcp:116135:9"/>
Wars) are ſo deer and precious to us, that we had rather our Lives ſhould breath out with them, than to live one moment after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of them.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I muſt confeſs I am to preſent you with a paper, ſomthing of a new kind, for we have had no longer time to conſider of it, than from Thurſday laſt, and Warrants (as we are informed) iſſuing out againſt us to take us, from thoſe that have no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; we durſt not well go our ordinary way to work, to get Subſcriptions to it, leſt we ſhould be ſurpriſed before we could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to this honorable Houſe, and ſo be fruſtrated in that benefit or relief that we juſtly expect from you; and to preſent it with a few hands, we judged inconſiderable in your eſtimation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore chuſe in the third place (being in ſo much haſt as we were to prevent our eminent and too apparent ruine) in perſon to bring it to your Bar, and avowedly to preſent it here: And therefore without any further queſtion, give me leave to tell you, I own it, and I know ſo doth all the reſt of my Friends preſent; and if any hazard ſhould enſue thereby, Give me leave reſolvedly to tell you, I am ſorry I have but one life to loſe, in maintaining the Truth, Juſtice, and Righteouſneſs, of ſo gallant a piece.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> We own this honorable Houſe (as of right) the true Guardian of our Liberties and Freedoms; and we wiſh and moſt heartily deſire, you would rouſe up your ſpirits (like men of gallantry) and now at laſt take unto your ſelves a magnanimous reſolution, to acquit your ſelves (without fear or dread) like the choſen and betruſted Truſtees of the People, from whom (as your ſelves acknowledge and declare) all juſt power is derived, to free us from all bondage and ſlavery, and really and truly inveſt us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the price of all our bloud, hazards, and toyls; Our Liberties and Freedoms, the true difference and diſtinction of men from beaſts.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> Though my spirit is full in the ſad apprehenſion of the dying condition of our Liberties and Freedoms: Yet at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I ſhall ſay no more, but in the behalf of my ſelf and my friends, I ſhall earneſtly entreat you to read theſe our ſerious Apprehenſions ſeriouſly, and debate them deliberately.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This we have adventured to publiſh for the timely information and benefit of all that adhere unto the common intereſt of the people, hoping that with ſuch, upon due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, it will find as large an acceptance, as our late Petition of <hi>Sept.</hi> 11. 1648. And we thought good (in regard we were not called in to receive an anſwer to the ſame) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, that we intend to ſecond it with a Petition ſufficiently ſubſcribed, we doubt not with many thouſands, earneſtly to ſolicite for an effectual Anſwer.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
